PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
- Recall that to figure out where a two-dimensional ray
- 回忆一下 为了解决二维的射线
intersects a line segment, we started by
和线段相交的问题 我们首先
first introducing a coordinate system.
引入了一个坐标系统
Once we have our coordinate system,
一旦我们有了我们的坐标系统
we can write our line AB in slope intercept form.
我们就可以用斜截式表示我们的直线 AB
Since in this example A has coordinates three two,
由于这个例子中 A 的坐标为 (3,2)
and B has coordinates four negative one,
B 坐标为 (4,-1)
the slope intercept form of AB
AB 的斜截式为
is y equals negative three x plus 11.
y=-3x+11
Similarly, if I pick P to have coordinates two, one half,
相似的 如果我选取 P 的坐标为 (2,-1/2)
then the slope intercept form of the ray CP
那么射线 CP 的斜截式为
is y equals one quarter x.
y=1/4x
The point I we're looking for is on both of these lines.
我们要找的点同时落在两条线上
So if I sub x and I sub y represent the coordinates of I,
所以如果 I_x 和 I_y 表示 I 的坐标
then I sub y equals negative three I sub x plus eleven,
那么 I_y = -3I_x+11
because I lies on AB.
是因为 I 落在 AB 上
And I sub y equals one quarter I sub x,
同样 I_y = 1/4I_x
because I lies on the ray CP.
是因为 I 落在射线 CP 上
Solving these two equations for the two unknowns
解这个二元方程组
gives us the coordinates I sub x and I sub y.
就给出了坐标 (I_x,I_y)
Using the slope intercept form
在二维中使用
of the ray works in two dimensions,
斜截式表示射线很有效
and is fairly simple to understand, but there's a problem
也很容易懂 当我们将它拓展至
when we generalize it to three dimensions.
三维空间中时就会出现一个问题
The problem is that in three dimensions,
那就是在三维空间中
the ray doesn't have a slope intercept form.
射线不能写成斜截式
So we'll have to throw out this representation of our ray
所以我们不得不将这种表示射线的方式抛弃掉
in preparation for three dimensional raytracing.
以便于我们进入三维光线追踪
To represent our ray CP, we'll use
为了表示我们的射线 CP 我们将使用
something called a parametric function.
被称为参数方程的东西
What I'm about to write looks a little strange at first,
我将要写的东西乍看起来有些奇怪
but bear with me, these functions start to
但要你和我打个赌 这些方程式
become familiar with practice.
会越用越熟练的
My ray will be represented by a new function, R of t,
我的射线将用一个新的方程表示 R(t)
that is the weighted average of C and P,
它是 C 与 P 的加权平均数
where t is the weight.
而 t 就是那个权重
In particular, I'm going to write R of t
特别的 我将把 R(t) 写做
as one minus t times C, plus t times P.
(1-t)*C+t*P
Notice what happens when t equals zero.
注意当 t 等于 0 时
One minus t is just one. So R of zero is C.
1-t 等于 1 所以 R(0) = C
And when t equals one, R of one equals P.
而当 t = 1 时 R(1) = P
That's convenient, because I can relabel C as R of zero,
这样做很方便 因为我可以把 C 写作 R(0)
and I can relabel P as R of one.
把 P 写作 R(1)
R of one half would be exactly halfway between C and P.
R(1/2) 将会得到 C 和 P 的中点
Values of t greater than one name points
当值 t 大于 1 时会让点
on the ray off in the scene beyond P.
沿 CP 移至场景内
Before we continue, get some experience
在我们继续前 从下个联系中
using this kind of parametric function in the next exercise. aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
掌握一些参数方程的经验吧 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox